Guide to the William Holland Thomas papers, 1814-1900s and undated RL.01290
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Infrastructure papers, 1828-1859; undated
  - Railroad Statistics, 1854-1855; Volume (paper); 9x14.5 cm; 30 pages (Volume S:3923)
    Haywood County, N.C. Includes distances by rail between various locales in N.C. and surrounding states. Also includes miscellaneous accounts.
  - Turnpike bonds, 1855-1856 (Box 5)
  - S.W. Gibson road accounts and payments, 1856 Oct. 1 (Box 5)
  - Act to incorporate Qualla Town and Ocanabuftas Turnpike Company: amendment for the N.C. General Assembly, 1857 (Box 5)
  - An Act to incorporate the Jonathan's Creek and Tennessee Mountain Turnpike Co. in the County of Haywood: amendment for the N.C. General Assembly, 1857 Jan. 8 (Box 5)
  - Turnpike Records, 1859; Volume (boards); 9.5x23 cm; 140 pages (Volume M:3928)
    Haywood County, N.C. Records expenses and accounts with shareholders of a turnpike.
  - An Act to amend the charter of the Western N.C. Railroad Company: N.C. General Assembly, 1859 Jan. 4 (Box 5)
  - An Act to incorporate the Western N.C. Rail Road Co.: amendments for the N.C. General Assembly, 1859 Feb. 21 (Box 5)
  - Appointment by the N.C. Board of Internal Improvement of William Holland Thomas as director on the Board of the Western N.C. Railroad Company, 1859 Nov. 28 (Box 5)
  - Turnpike charters (incomplete), undated (Box 5)
  - Agreement to grant right-of-way to the Blue Ridge or Rabun Gap Railroad, undated (Box 5)
  - Letter by William Johnston, in relation to railroad, etc. (incomplete), undated (Box 5)
  - A Bill to secure the payment of tolls to the state of N.C. on the Western Turnpike, undated (Box 5)
- Cherokee papers, 1823-1876; undated
  This series includes a wide range of material documenting the legal and financial status of North Carolina Cherokees during the early 19th century. It includes copies and correspondence regarding several treaties between the U.S. government and the Cherokee chiefs; powers of attorney for various Cherokee families who relied on Thomas to support their interests to the Dept. of the Interior; censuses of Cherokee remaining in North Carolina following the Indian Removal Acts; legal depositions, opinions, and complaints involving Cherokee land claims; crime by and against Cherokee people; pensions and relief due the Cherokees; and compensation collected by Thomas according to the terms of the various Indian treaties. There are also volumes of customer accounts designated by Thomas as "Indian Books" kept by him and his employees at his various stores; additional documentation of Cherokee financial accounts can be found on loose pages in the General Papers series and in other account books in the Financial Materials series.
  - Cherokee Account Book, 1823-1835 (Box 5)
  - Conditions under which the Cherokees enrolled and emigrated West, 1828-1834 (Box 5)
  - List of claims filed for the action of the board of Cherokee Commissioners under the 17th Act of the Treaty of 1835 (Box 5)
  - Supplementary Report of Cherokee Indians Remaining in N.C., 1835-1840; Volume (paper); 19x30 cm; 50 pages (Volume L:3927)
    Haywood County, N.C. Census and records of Cherokee families living in N.C., including ages and notes about their location.
  - Opinion of the Cherokee Commissions on the claim of Wacheechah/Grasshopper, for value of a preemption, 1835 (Box 5)
  - "333 Indians belonging to the Town Qualla," including lists of Cherokee and verifications by white citizens, 1835-1837 (Box 5)
  - Part of the evidence of the heirs of deceased Cherokees (excerpts, in Cherokee), 1838 (Box 5)
  - The United States to W.H. Thomas, to furnishing the following named poor Indians with corn in the year 1839 in the spring (Box 5)
  - Indian Book debts remaining due this store, 1839 Dec. 1 (Box 5)
  - Census of the N.C. Cherokee, 1840 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Lands and Com. purchased for Indians, 1841-1842 (Box 5)
    Bound item with entries for Buffalo and Qualla Town, as well as journal entries (presumably from Thomas) dating from February and March 1842. Acquired as Acc. 2018-0106.
  - Claim of Coticawa or Cinthio Young Deer re: payment for property from which she was dispossessed, 1844 Sept. 30 (Box 5)
  - Application by Western Cherokee for fulfillment of guarantees made by U.S., written to William Wilkins, Secretary of War, 1844-1845 (undated) (Box 5)
  - List of Cherokee claims filed by William Holland Thomas as attorney; filed before Board of Commissioners, 1847 (Box 5)
  - Cherokee of Buffalo (names and ages) entitled to interest under Act of July 29 1848 (Box 5)
  - Location of Tracts in the different towns in Cherokee Nation (including Wolf Town, Paint Town, Deer Town, and Pretty Face Town), 1848 (Box 5)
  - Census of the Cherokees under the Act of July 29 1848, approximately 1848 (Box 5)
  - List of suspended Cherokee claims made under the Act of 1838, 1849 (Box 5)
  - Cherokees entitled to pensions from U.S. for service in War of 1812 (re: fighting Creek Indians), 1850 (Box 5)
  - Petition to N.C. General Assembly for relief of solvent purchases of Cherokee lands, 1850 (Box 5)
  - Copies of testimony in the case of James R. Love vs. William H. Thomas, 1850 (Box 5)
  - Persons (Cherokees) who died in Haywood Co., N.C., 1850 (Box 5)
  - Waddy Thompson argument in relation to the Cherokee, N.C., 1851 Mar. 9 (Box 6)
  - Attorney General Jonathan Crittenden: opinion on the Cherokee Treaties, sent to H. H. Stuart, Secretary of Interior, 1851 Apr. 16 (Box 6)
  - Attorney General Jonathan Crittenden opinion to H. H. Stuart, re: payment of attorney fees for agents Waddy Thompson and Arnold Harris, 1851 Apr. 26 (Box 6)
  - Copy (unsigned) of letter to Commissioner of Indian Affairs Luke Lea rejecting claims by agents Thompson and Harris, 1851 May 1 (Box 6)
  - List of deposits of money by Cherokees for purchases of lands: Wolf Town, Paint Town, Pretty Woman Town, 1851 (Box 6)
  - Statement showing the names of the Cherokee Indians in the neighborhood of Murphy, N.C., intilled to interest on 53.33 dollars and the amount due each, 1857 Jul. 29 (Box 6)
  - Resolutions of the North Carolina Cherokees, 1859 Oct. 29 (Box 6)
  - List of the Indians supposed to have died in Cherokee County N.C. administered upon by S.P. Sherrill, 1867 Jul. 10 (Box 6)
  - Cherokee Reservation Record taken at Murphy, N.C., 1868 Nov.-Dec. (Box 6)
  - Ledger / List of Indians Living on Catugajay Creek, N.C., 1839-1845, 1870; Volume (calf and boards); 22x34 cm; 150 pages (Volume F:3912)
    Cherokee County, N.C. Multi-purpose volume. First portion is customer accounts and store accounts. Second portion is a census of Cherokee "on the Catugajay Creek, Macon Co., living on the land of William Siler Esq." The Cherokee residents are listed with an assigned number, including their names and relevant notes. Many deceased Cherokee are also noted. Some of the pages in this ledger are mutilated and torn.
  - Deposition of George T. Mason, witness before the Commission in certain Indian suits in Statesville, N.C., 1874 Oct. 17 (Box 6)
  - Indian Book, 1837; Volume (paper); 12x33 cm; 90 pages (Volume ff:3897)
    Shole Creek (Shoal Creek), Cherokee Co., N.C. Alphabetical index with Cherokee names and unidentified quantities of money (accounts?).
  - Ledger and Indian Accounts ("Indian Book"), 1840-1859; Volume (calf and boards); 26x38 cm; 500 pages (Volume F:3914)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Customer accounts, presumably of Cherokee although it is not always clear. Includes purchases and expenses, listed by name.
  - Indian Book, 1857; Volume (paper); 8x12.5 cm; 18 pages (Volume S:3898)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C. Entries are dated, but otherwise entirely in Cherokee language.
  - Powers of attorney, 1837-1876; 6 folders (Box 6)
    Most of these grant powers of attorney to William Holland Thomas from individual Cherokee.
  - Register of Reservations Under the Cherokee Treaty of 1817, undated; Volume (boards); 21x26 cm; 72 pages (Volume M:3924)
    North Carolina and Tennessee. Alternative title: "Register of persons who wish reservations under the Treaty of July 8, 1817." Includes names and places of residence and occasionally other remarks such as "enrolled for Arkansas."
  - List of William Holland Thomas's powers of attorney from Cherokees East, and their claims, undated (Box 6)
  - Names and valuations of allowed Cherokee Reservations, undated (Box 6)
  - Cherokee Indian accounts, Murphy store, undated (Box 6)
  - Claims of the Cherokees East, undated (Box 6)
  - Indian Lands/Indian Tax List purchased as trustee for Cherokee, undated (Box 6)
  - List of claims/claimants for preemptions, Buffalo, N.C., undated (Box 6)
  - Statement showing the names of Cherokee Indians who reside East of the Mississippi ... and the amount due to each for their claims ... under the treaty of 1835-1836, undated (Box 6)
  - Indian accounts written in the Indian language (Cherokee), undated (Box 6)
  - List of sums of money paid to the Cherokees through their attorney William Holland Thomas, undated (Box 6)
  - Payments made to William Holland Thomas for fees in the per capita case (Cherokees), undated (Box 6)
  - List of Buffalo Cherokee and payments under the act of July 29, 1838, S. P. Sherrill, undated (Box 6)
  - A list of Cherokee claimants residing in Qualla Town, N.C., undated (Box 6)
  - Roll of Reservations to Cherokees by the Treaties of 1817 and 1819, undated (Box 6)
  - Department of the Interior. Office of Indian Affairs. Certified copies of Cherokee reservation claims, 1856-1874, undated (Box 6)
  - List of deeds for land in Indian boundary, 1831-1868, undated (Box 6)
  - List of names of Cherokee and clans to which they belong, undated (Box 6)
    Including Paint Town, Wolf Town, Pretty Woman Town, Deer Town, and Bird Town
  - List of persons entitled to Reservations under 1819 Treaty with the Cherokees, undated (Box 6)
  - Rejected claims of George W. Churchwill left with William Holland Thomas, undated (Box 6)
  - Land surveys, Bird Town, N.C. by George Mason, undated (Box 6)
  - Persons who had died on the census of 1838, undated (Box 6)
  - Explanation of the rights and claims of the Cherokee Indians remaining in the States east of the Mississippi, addressed to H. Conner, Charleston, undated (Box 6)
  - Cherokee Indians vs. Thomas: original answer of James R. Thomas, undated (Box 6)
  - List of names of Cherokee Indians who are supposed to have been engaged in the late war between the U.S. and the Confederate States, undated (Box 6)
    Including whether allied with Union or Confederate side (sometimes, both sides)
  - William Holland Thomas claim for subsisting Euchalla and his band of Cherokees, including statement explaining the case, undated (Box 6)
    Re: Charley and his band of outlaws
  - List of Cherokee Indians that aided in capturing Charley and his band of outlaws, undated (Box 6)
  - Register of the names of Cherokees allowed citizenship, undated (Box 6)
  - Names and number of Cherokees on Valley River, undated (Box 6)
  - Account Book ("An estimate of land purchased lying on Soco Creek in Haywood County, the price paid for them, the No. of Acres, from whom purchased"), 1836-1841; Volume (paper); 16x18.5 cm; 40 pages (Volume M:3852)
    Haywood County, N.C. Records of land purchased for Cherokee in Quallatown. Pages 8-40ish are blank. More text on last page.
  - Account Book ("Book account of cloth sold on Smoky mounts to the Indians"), 1838; Volume (paper); 17x19 cm; 25 pages (Volume M:3856)
    Haywood County, N.C. Accounts of cloth sales by Robert Collins to Cherokee, including amount and customer names. Middle portion of booklet is blank. There are also accounts at the end of the booklet with additional Cherokee names.
- Personal papers, 1853-1889; undated
  Thomas's assorted personal materials, including scrapbooks, that document his role as a community leader in Haywood County as well as inventories of his personal library.
  - Scrapbook, 1852-1888; Volume (boards); 23x34 cm; 120 pages (Volume F:3925)
    Jackson County, N.C. Clippings and pencilled notes by Thomas on a range of political topics and figures.
  - Scrapbook, approximately 1890; Volume (boards); 24x30 cm; 15 pages (Volume L:3926)
    Waynesville, N.C. Scrapbook with valentines, printed pictures/clippings kept by unknown Thomas. Mutilated.
  - Unsigned draft of a letter to the editor of Pickens Courier, 1853 Sept. 1 (Box 5)
  - N.C. Superintendent of Public Instruction: blank forms for county officials, 1885-1889 (Box 5)
  - "Standridge Book", undated (Box 5)
  - Webster Township, Jackson Co., N.C. petition to Congress for funding of schools, undated (Box 5)
  - Old North State poem/ballad, undated (Box 5)
  - Books bought by William Holland Thomas at sale/auction, undated (Box 5)
  - Catalogue of books held by William Holland Thomas, undated (Box 5)